Guide to the Barbara Isted Collection of Thomas Percy
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Barbara Isted collection of Thomas Percy
1754-1812
GEN MSS 465
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
Correspondence, writings, and other papers of and about Thomas Percy, preserved by his daughter Barbara Isted and mainly concerning Percy and Isted family matters, such as inheritances and the death of Barbara Isted's infant daughter. Includes manuscripts of "Oh Nanny wilt thou gang wi' me" and another poem written to his wife, as well as obituaries, copies of his will, genealogies, and copies of poems by other writers.
Isted, Barbara Percy
Percy, Thomas, 1729-1811
Percy, Thomas, 1729-1811 ( Oh Nanny wilt thou gang wi' me)
Shenton, Robert ( Oh Nanny wilt thou gang wi' me)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Hoffman and Freeman with funds from the Edwin J. Beinecke legacy, December 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Thomas Percy (1729-1811), English clergyman and poet, was educated at Oxford and Cambridge, and became vicar of Easton-Maudit, Northamptonshire, in 1753. While at Easton-Maudit he served in several other ecclesiastic roles, including chaplain to the King. In 1782 he was made Bishop of Dromore, in County Down, Ireland, a position he held until his death.
Percy married Anne Gutteridge in 1759. Of their six children, only two, Barbara and Elizabeth, survived into adulthood. Barbara married Colonel Samuel Isted of Ecton, Northamptonshire, in 1795, and had two children: Ambrose, born February 15, 1797, and Anne, who died in 1801. Elizabeth Percy married Pierce Meade, Archdeacon of Dromore, in 1801. Anne (Gutteridge) Percy died at Dromore in 1807.
Percy was well respected in his time for his own writing as well as for his translations of Chinese and Icelandic verse, among other works. He is best known for editing a collection of poems titled Reliques of Ancient English Poetry, published in 1765, and for a popular song known as "Oh Nanny wilt thou gang wi' me," first published in Robert Dodsley's Collection of Poems in 1758 under the title "A Song" and said to be written for his future wife. Percy's literary friends included Samuel Johnson and William Shenstone, and he was related to Lord Percy, Duke of Northumberland.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains papers of and concerning Thomas Percy preserved by his daughter Barbara Isted. The papers span the years 1754-1812, and consist primarily of family correspondence, but also include writings of Thomas Percy, copies of his will, obituaries, poems by other writers, and a few other papers. Notes in Barbara Isted's hand accompany many of the papers. The collection is organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, contains letters to and from Thomas Percy, and a few other family letters. Percy's outgoing correspondence includes letters to his wife, his daughter Barbara, and his son-in-law Samuel Isted, and part of a letter to a Mr. Binnel discussing Percy's translation of the Song of Solomon and describing his work collecting old songs for what would become Ancient Reliques of English Poetry. Incoming correspondence consists chiefly of letters from his daughters concerning the Isted children. Other Correspondence includes a letter from Elizabeth (Percy) Meade describing her father's death, a detailed description of the child Anne Isted's funeral, and various letters of condolence.
Series II, Writings, contains manuscripts of two poems Percy wrote to his wife Anne, clippings from his diary, and notes on the Northamptonshire dialect. The manuscript of the poem beginning "Oh Nannie wilt thou gang wi' me" is titled "A Song in Imitation of ye Scotch Mann[e]r;" with it is a related clipping from his diary and the first page of a musical setting of the poem by, according to Isted, the Reverend Robert Shenton, a college friend of Percy's. Also present is a manuscript copy, in Anne Percy's hand, of a poem titled "Verses on Leaving Wolverhampton in a very Tempest[u]ous Night," also known as "To Annie I must go." The clippings from the diary document events significant to Percy's family during the years 1782-1801, including itemized descriptions of his daughters' inheritances.
Series III, Other Papers, contains copies of his will, obituaries, genealogical notes, a copy of a letter from Lord Raby to Lord Hallifax titled by Percy "A Character of Charles XII King of Sweden," and manuscript copies of poems by various authors, including Swift, Sir Charles Hanbury Williams, Lord Cornwallis, and Lady Winchelsea.
Authors, English -- 18th century; Children -- Death; Clergy -- Great Britain; Dowry -- Great Britain; English literature -- Musical settings; English poetry -- 18th century; Isted, Barbara Percy; Isted, Samuel; Meade, Elizabeth Percy; Percy, Anne Gutteridge; Percy, Thomas, 1729-1811
- I. Correspondence, 1762-1811; .12' (12 folders)
  - THOMAS PERCY
    - Outgoing
      - Binnel, Mr., AL fragment, 1762 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Isted, Barbara Percy, 1 ALS and 1 letter in the hand of a third party, initialled T.P., 1800-09 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Isted, Samuel 2 ALS, 1797-1800 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Percy, Anne Gutteridge, 3 ALS and 1 AL fragment, 1782-97 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Incoming
      - Isted, Barbara Percy, 2 ALS, 1801-08 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Meade, Elizabeth Percy, and Barbara Percy Isted, ALS, 1801 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Unknown correspondents, 1 AL fragment, 1 unrelated envelope addressed to Northumberland House, 1808 Oct 3, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - OTHER CORRESPONDENCE
    - Meade, Elizabeth Percy, ALS to Pierce Meade, Barbara Percy Isted and Samuel Isted, 1811 Oct 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Northumberland, [Duke of], ALS to Samuel Isted, 1807 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Stott, J., ALS to Barbara Percy Isted, 1811 Oct 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Scope and Contents
      Contains poem "Lines hastily written on returning home from the Bishop of Dromore's Funeral, Oct 4, 1811"
    - Whalley, [P.?], ALS to Samuel Isted, 1801 Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Worcester, J., ALS to Lord Digby, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- II. Writings, 1754-1801; .03' (4 folders)
  - Diary or memorandum book, fragments clipped from, 1782-1801 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ["O Nanny wilt thou gang wi' me,"] manuscript and musical setting, 1754 Apr (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Manuscript of ballad titled "A Song in Imitation of ye Scotch Mann[e]r" and first page only of music manuscript titled "A Scotch Song by T. P. set by R. S. [Robert Shenton];" with undated clipping from TP's diary and notes by Barbara Isted
  - "Northamptonshire Words and Phrases," manuscript notes, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Verses on Leaving Wolverhampton in a very Tempest[u]ous Night" ["To Annie I must go"], manuscript poem, 1758 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    In Anne Percy's handwriting
- III. Other Papers, 1777-1812; .06' (6 folders)
  - Will and memorandum regarding will, manuscript copies by Barbara Isted, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Obituaries, 1811-12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Genealogies of Percy and Isted familes, 1796-1812 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Manuscript copies of poems by various authors in Latin and English (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes poems by Dean [Jonathan?] Swift, Sir Charles Hanbury Williams, Lord Cornwallis, and Lady Winchelsea
  - "A Character of Charles XII King of Sweden," manuscript copy of letter from Lord Raby to Lord Hallifax, 1707, 1777 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Empty enclosures with inscriptions by Barbara Isted, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)